Guide to the Edward Featherston Small Papers, 1884-1921 and undated RL.11260
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edward Featherston Small
1884-1921 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Small, Edward Featherston, 1844-1924
RL.11260
0.5 Linear Feet
Edward Featherston Small was a photographer and salesman for the W. Duke, Sons and Co. tobacco company in Durham, N.C. His papers include correspondence regarding the W. Duke, Sons and Co. sales tactics during the 1880s as well as typescript drafts by Small, including some undated autobiographical essays and a 1907 history of his work for the W. Duke, Sons and Co.
Biographical / Historical
Edward Featherston Small (1844-1924) was a Confederate veteran, photographer, and salesman for the W. Duke, Sons and Co. tobacco company in Durham, N.C.
More about Small can be found here: http://ncpedia.org/biography/small-edward-featherston
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Edward Featherston Small Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1939.
Collection Overview
Collection includes correspondence between Small and W. Duke, Sons and Co. representatives, as well as occasional letters from J.B. Duke. Also contained are drafts and excerpts of drafts prepared by Small discussing his service in the Confederate Army, his sales career for the W. Duke, Sons and Co. Tobacco firm, and other anecdotal autobiographical essays. Collection contains 1 portrait photograph of Small, and 2 photographs that appear to be of Small and his telescope and an accompanying image of an eclipse. All photographs are undated. There is also an undated draft of a Civil War memoir written by Small's wife, Julia Telfair Small.
Advertising -- Cigarettes -- United States; Traveling sales personnel -- Correspondence; Atlanta (Ga.) -- Commerce; Durham (N.C.) -- Industry; Veterans -- Confederate States of America; Memoirs and biographies; Tobacco industry -- United States; Small, Edward Featherston, 1844-1924; Small, Julia Telfair; W. Duke, Sons & Co.; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; American Tobacco Company
- Information folder, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1884-1890, 1907-1921 and undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
- W. Duke, Sons and Co. account sheet for E. Small, 1887-1888 (Box 1)
- Clippings re: Small's salesman career (including coverage of polo matches), 1880s and 1921 (Box 1)
- Clippings re: Small's personal activities in Atlanta, Georgia, 1922 and undated (Box 1)
- Clippings re: Small and his tobacco sales career, reported in Durham, Gastonia, High Point, and Salisbury, NC, 1921-1922 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  These clippings all appear to relate to Small's 1921 journey through North Carolina to attend a reunion of Confederate veterans.
- Untitled autobiographical sketch (6 pages), undated (Box 1)
- The Forgotten Man Behind the Throne of the American Tobacco Co., undated (Box 1)
  Set of notecards outlining a proposed article or speech.
- A Correct Version of the Beginnings of the Trust, 1907 and undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  Contains two typescript draft versions, one with edits.
- "Just a Thought" blurbs/vignettes, undated (Box 1)
- Jeoffry Stark, The Tar Heel, or the Vaudeville Life of a Johnnie Reb, undated; 4 folders (Box 1)
  Contains two relatively complete drafts of Small's autobiographical narrative about his Confederate service, as well as two additional folders of manuscript and typescript draft excerpts and notes created by Small as he prepared the work. Jeoffry Stark is a pseudonym for Small.
- A Leaf from the Old South, undated (Box 1)
  Typescript draft of an memoir prepared by Small's wife, Julia Telfair Small, recounting her childhood and experience during the Civil War in Smithfield, North Carolina.
- Photograph of Edward Featherston Small, undated (Box 1)
- Two photographs re: Small's astronomy (eclipse and Small with telescope), undated (Box 1)